<CHAPTER NUMBER="6"><TL-CHAP VL="BG" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Това е Европа - Дебат с Петери Орпо, министър-председател на Финландия (разискване)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="ES" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Esto es Europa - Debate con Petteri Orpo, primer ministro de Finlandia (debate)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="CS" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">To je Evropa – rozprava s finským premiérem Petterim Orpem (rozprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="DA" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Dette er Europa - Debat med Finlands premierminister, Petteri Orpo (forhandling)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="DE" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Was Europa ausmacht – Aussprache mit dem Ministerpräsidenten von Finnland, Petteri Orpo (Aussprache)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="ET" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">See on Euroopa – arutelu Soome peaministri Petteri Orpoga (arutelu)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="EL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Αυτή είναι η Ευρώπη - Συζήτηση με τον πρωθυπουργό της Φινλανδίας, Petteri Orpo (συζήτηση)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="EN" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">This is Europe - Debate with the Prime Minister of Finland, Petteri Orpo (debate)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="FR" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">C’est l’Europe - Débat avec le Premier ministre finlandais, Petteri Orpo (débat)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="IT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Questa è l&apos;Europa - Discussione con Petteri Orpo, primo ministro della Finlandia (discussione)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="LV" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Debates &quot;Šī ir Eiropa&quot;: piedalās Somijas premjerministrs Petteri Orpo (debates)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="LT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Tai – Europa. Diskusijos su Suomijos Ministru Pirmininku Petteri Orpo (diskusijos)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="HU" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Ez Európa – Vita Petteri Orpo finn miniszterelnökkel (vita)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="MT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Din hija l-Ewropa - Dibattitu ma’ Petteri Orpo, Prim Ministru tal-Finlandja (dibattitu)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="NL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Dit is Europa – Debat met Petteri Orpo, premier van Finland (debat)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="PL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Oto Europa – Debata z udziałem premiera Finlandii Petteriego Orpo (debata)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="PT" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Isto é a Europa - Debate com o primeiro-ministro da Finlândia, Petteri Orpo (debate)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="RO" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Aceasta este Europa - Dezbatere cu prim-ministrul Finlandei, Petteri Orpo (dezbatere)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="SK" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Toto je Európa – diskusia s predsedom vlády Fínska Petterim Orpom (rozprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="SL" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">To je Evropa – razprava s predsednikom finske vlade Petterijem Orpom (razprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="FI" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Tämä on Eurooppa – keskustelu Suomen pääministerin Petteri Orpon kanssa (keskustelu)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="SV" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Detta är Europa – debatt med Finlands statsminister Petteri Orpo (debatt)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="HR" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Ovo je Europa - rasprava s finskim premijerom Petterijem Orpom (rasprava)</TL-CHAP><TL-CHAP VL="GA" TYPE="OTHER" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.576" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:29.000">Seo í an Eoraip - Díospóireacht le Príomh-Aire na Fionlainne, Petteri Orpo (díospóireacht)</TL-CHAP><NUMERO ACT="3-056-0000" PRE="3-054-0000" SUIV="3-057-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:37:56.586" VOD-END="2024-03-13T10:40:31.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="118859" CODICT="118859" LIB="Roberta | Metsola"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">President. – </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA>Dear colleagues, good morning – <EMPHAS NAME="I">hyvää huomenta. </EMPHAS>I am delighted to announce that we have the Prime Minister of Finland, Petteri Orpo, with us today.</PARA><PARA>Dear Prime Minister, dear Petteri, welcome to the European Parliament. Thank you for accepting our invitation to address this House as part of our ‘This is Europe’ series of debates.</PARA><PARA>Finland is a nation I know well and one that I can say holds a very special place in my heart. But allow me now on behalf of all Members of this House to reiterate the European Parliament’s appreciation for Finland’s commitment to the European Union – over your thirty year membership – to our shared values, and particularly for your support to Ukraine and to our collective security.</PARA><PARA>Thank you, Prime Minister, for your personal leadership and your resolve towards strengthening our European project, for Finland’s support to a free and democratic Ukraine, and I wish to commend you on steering Finland towards NATO membership.</PARA><PARA>Having a 1 400 kilometre border with Russia means that Finland is uniquely qualified to lead when it comes to Europe’s security and defence. It also means that Finland has faced hybrid threats in recent weeks and months that have put pressure on our systems. We understand that our security architecture must be able to respond to the level of threat our way of life is facing.</PARA><PARA>Finland has benefitted from close to EUR 2 billion in recovery and resilience funds that will support Finland’s economy in the digital and green transition, and RePowerEU cleantech funds will continue to support Finland’s innovation and businesses on the road to sustainable growth. This is important to underline.</PARA><PARA>And it is important – as I said in Helsinki last week – that as many Finnish citizens as possible continue to help shape the future of Europe and go out to vote in the European Parliament elections on 9 June.</PARA><PARA>Dear Prime Minister, dear Petteri, the floor is yours.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-057-0000" PRE="3-056-0000" SUIV="3-058-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T10:40:30.876" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:02:15.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="PRIME MINISTER OF FINLAND"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="0" CODICT="253625" LIB="Petteri | Orpo" SPEAKER_TYPE="prime minister of finland"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Petteri Orpo,</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> <EMPHAS NAME="I">Prime Minister of Finland</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Madam Speaker, dear Roberta, honourable Members of the European Parliament, fellow Europeans, it’s good to see you. Many familiar faces here today.</PARA><PARA>I am happy to be here at the European Parliament – a building I have visited numerous times, previously as Minister of Agriculture and Forestry, Minister of the Interior and Minister of Finance.</PARA><PARA>Today, I stand before you not just as the Prime Minister of Finland but also as a committed European, eager to share Finland’s vision for a resilient, competitive and secure Europe. </PARA><PARA>Now we find ourselves at a key moment in history, one that calls for our courage, unity and determination. We have returned to the very fundaments of European integration: promoting peace and defending our values. The ongoing war in Ukraine is not just a conflict on our continent’s borders; it is a stark reminder of the fragility of our peace. It threatens the very principles on which our Union was built. As Europeans, it is high time for us to wake up and smell the coffee. This is the defining challenge of our generation and our continent.</PARA><PARA>Finland, which shares a long border – more than 1 300 kilometres – with Russia, understands the significance of this moment. Finland has never dropped the ball when it comes to security and defence. After the Cold War, we remained committed to maintaining a credible and independent defence capacity.</PARA><PARA>Our decision to join NATO is not one we took lightly; it was a clear signal of our commitment to European security. Now we are happy to finally welcome our close neighbour Sweden to the Alliance. Welcome.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>The war in Ukraine has been a wake-up call for all of us. We must never again be so reliant on others for our energy and security. We must take care of our own defence. Ramping up our defence industry, improving our preparedness and strengthening our borders are critical pillars of our shared security architecture. We are living in a time where practically all policy fields are linked to our security, and without security, we cannot ensure a prosperous future for Europe.</PARA><PARA>For us in Finland, the EU is the most important political and economic frame of reference and community of values. My Government is committed to a strong European Union – an EU that acts, not only reacts. We want to build a Union that takes care of our common security and works for our economy. Upholding the rule of law in Europe must remain our core principle.</PARA><PARA>Today I have three main points for the future of Europe and the next mandate.</PARA><PARA>First, we have to strengthen Europe’s strategic competitiveness. The reason our economic competitiveness is so crucial is simple. Europe is falling behind in productivity. Our standard of living is diminishing compared to others. The United States and China are experiencing faster growth and attracting investments. Should this trend persist, we will no longer be able to stand on our own feet.</PARA><PARA>We must build our competitiveness by developing our strengths and through market-based solutions, with a fully functioning internal market at the core. This foundation will enable us to thrive in an increasingly competitive global landscape.</PARA><PARA>We need to cut the bureaucratic red tape, implement sustainable fiscal policies, reform labour market regulation, and conclude new trade deals. We must foster innovation and skills, strengthen our internal market and ensure significant funding for innovation and research.</PARA><PARA>These initiatives are the bedrock of long-term competitiveness. There is an immense need to finance our defence and the green transition, as well as broader competitiveness-enhancing policy areas like research and innovation.</PARA><PARA>We must also utilise existing instruments more effectively. This means reforming the next MFF and seeking more financial resources from the markets, for example through the EIB and by developing the Capital Markets Union. We need a true European Investment Union. It is essential that we make investing in Europe attractive again.</PARA><PARA>The urgency of reverting the State aid rules to their normal framework has become increasingly apparent. The escalation of State aid competition threatens the very core of our single market. Such competition can lead to a race to the bottom, where countries with deeper pockets can unfairly support their domestic industries.</PARA><PARA>The principle of a single market is founded on equal opportunities for all, not a fragmented landscape where walls are built and financial muscle overshadows market dynamics. It is crucial that we restore the normal State aid rules. A healthy single market benefits all European citizens and business – today and in the long term.</PARA><PARA>Jacques Delors, father of the European single market, would indeed be deeply concerned by the current practices regarding the relaxation of State aid rules. The dilution of these rules risks undermining the level playing field Delors worked so tirelessly to establish.</PARA><PARA>When it comes to our trade policy, we must refocus on the core principles of trade policy itself. Our setbacks have often stemmed from pursuing broad-ranging agreements with noble intentions and expecting our negotiating partners to commit to them. If we want to be globally relevant, we need a better ability to conclude, ratify and implement trade deals, not a better ability to bring them down. </PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>The European Union’s trade policy is not only a vital instrument for boosting competitiveness; it has become crucial in building partnerships in today’s global landscape.</PARA><PARA>Friends, secondly, we have to improve European comprehensive security. This includes defence and border security, but also preparedness more broadly. </PARA><PARA>Firstly, ramping up our defence industry is priority number one. The European Union has the regulation and the resources, and we need to use those tools. Even as a member of NATO, we think that Europe can do a lot. NATO and the EU do not exclude each other – they complement each other.</PARA><PARA>Next, on border security, Russia has weaponised migration to put pressure on Finland and the entire EU. Russia is pushing third country nationals towards our eastern land border. This is not acceptable. The numbers are still relatively low, but the phenomenon is worrisome. If we can’t stop this phenomenon now, it will also become a question of numbers and a greater threat to national and European security. Security at the EU’s external borders is at the core of the EU’s existence.</PARA><PARA>Safeguarding our external front lines against any form of hybrid attacks is crucial. This is why our response has been decisive. We have closed our eastern land border and are in the process of preparing new legislation. We are doing this to protect the entire European Union. A hybrid attack on our border is a hybrid attack against the whole of Europe. Therefore, we need to evaluate our existing European legislation, to see whether it is strong enough to tackle these challenges in its current state. If not, then we must consider updating it to better suit the time we are living in. We must send a clear message: Europe is resolute in its defence, agile in its response, and firm in its commitment to the safety of its borders.</PARA><PARA>In addressing the security of our borders, we must also focus on the people who live in these critical areas. Tourism and all cross-border trade has stopped indefinitely. The vitality of the EU’s external border regions is crucial, not just for national security but for the cohesion of our society. The war has caused the economic base in these border areas to decline. This trend, if unchanged, will lead to depopulation and pose a grave risk to the security and stability of our Union. It is necessary that we implement EU-level policies aimed at revitalising these areas and making them more secure against external threats.</PARA><PARA>On preparedness. Preparedness for crises is one of the cornerstones of security. The EU and its Member States must be better prepared for a growing number of increasingly complex crises, as we have learned from the COVID-19 crisis, the war in Ukraine and the energy crisis. It is in everyone’s interest to improve the level of preparedness of all Member States and the EU as a whole.</PARA><PARA>In this context of preparedness, Finland stands ready to share our experiences of resilience and readiness. Our nation has long been recognised as a superpower in preparedness. It is a status born out of necessity and reinforced by our history and geopolitical position.</PARA><PARA>We have developed comprehensive strategies that cover all sectors of society, from public to private. Our approach to preparedness includes not only physical defences but also societal resilience, which is critical in facing both conventional and hybrid threats.</PARA><PARA>I believe Finland’s model of preparedness could offer valuable lessons for the European Union. By adopting similar comprehensive and forward-thinking strategies, we can enhance the resilience of the entire Union.</PARA><PARA>This is why we ask the Commission to develop and publish the first EU strategy for a Preparedness Union. This should be based on a whole-of-society approach, where the needs and contributions of all political sectors are taken into account.</PARA><PARA>We are not suggesting another policy document; we are calling for an innovative blueprint that ensures the European Union’s resilience in the face of complex challenges.</PARA><PARA>Our third priority has to do with the environment and climate. With the right kind of climate policy, we can strengthen our security of supply, boost our economies and improve the supply of European raw materials. The Government of Finland is committed to reaching the climate goals. We think that while tackling climate change, we can also create jobs and phase out fossil fuels. We have the technology and know-how for this here in Europe.</PARA><PARA>We must emphasise a clean transition that leverages the bioeconomy and circular economy. With clean energy – in the form of nuclear power, wind power, solar power and biomass – we will attract industry that can produce and export these clean solutions.</PARA><PARA>We should combat climate change and support biodiversity in a way that recognises the diverse circumstances across the Member States. A technology-neutral, cost-effective clean transition will pave the way for sustainable growth. The bioeconomy and renewable natural resources are our allies in reducing emissions and diminishing harmful dependencies on third countries. </PARA><PARA>As we look towards the next legislative term, it is important to admit that our environmental and climate goals cannot be achieved through more regulation alone. Regulation has been necessary and will continue to be, but our approach thus far has focused too much on the details, losing sight of the broader picture.</PARA><PARA>We must have proper impact assessments. In the upcoming term, we must recalibrate our climate policy and shift away from overly detailed regulation to fostering innovation. We need carrots and incentives, not sticks and bureaucracy.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>As I approach the end of my speech, I will turn back to the situation in Ukraine. I say it is our job as leaders to fight against any pessimism and to show an example and leadership. Everyone has to wake up.</PARA><PARA>Russia continues to commit war crimes in Ukraine. It has shifted to a war economy. Russia is evidently preparing for a long conflict with the West and represents a permanent and existential military threat to Europe. If we, as a united Europe, fail to respond sufficiently to this challenge, the coming years will be filled with danger and the looming threat of attack.</PARA><PARA>We must bolster our support for Ukraine now for it to win this war and at the same time enhance our own defence capabilities and the ability to defend ourselves.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>It is also essential that we offer a credible European path forward for Ukraine. Enlargement of the EU is a geopolitical necessity and a question of security.</PARA><PARA>Ukraine has demonstrated its ability to defend itself, and the Ukrainian people’s resolve remains high. Their resilience and determination pose a significant challenge to Russian interests. Supporting Ukraine is not only a moral imperative but also a strategic necessity. The cost of Russian military success would far exceed the investment required to support Ukraine. Imagine what will happen next if Russia succeeds.</PARA><PARA>I say that every euro spent on Ukraine today is a low price compared to the alternative costs if Russia wins. </PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>We have already taken significant steps, but more must be done. Ukraine is fighting, and we have the resources to support it. Ukraine deserves a just and lasting peace on its own terms. Securing the agreement on the EU’s Ukraine Facility among all 27 Member States was crucial.</PARA><PARA>Next, we need to deliver on ammunition production and agree on additional funding for the European Peace Facility and Ukraine Assistance Fund as quickly as possible. Finland is doing its share: we have increased our ammunition production, and I urge all Member States to do the same.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>It is crucial to recognise that Russia’s military capabilities are limited, despite its attempts to hide this fact. Russia is not invincible. We can overcome this challenge if we pool our resources together. We have the financial means, now we need to demonstrate our political commitment. Self-satisfaction is no longer an option; our collective future depends on our ability to recognise and counteract the threats posed by an aggressive and militarised Russia.</PARA><PARA>Strengthening our defence is not just a matter of national security – it is a precondition for preserving the peace and stability that have long been the hallmarks of European integration and prosperity.</PARA><PARA>In this light, we have to amplify the European Investment Bank’s engagement in security and defence financing. </PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>Recognising the EIB’s pivotal role in investment financing and as the EU’s lending arm, there is an urgent call to extend its capabilities beyond dual-use projects, especially in response to the growing demands within the European security and defence sectors.</PARA><PARA>Friends, more Europe doesn’t and shouldn’t mean less America. The United States is and will be our most important ally and we must strengthen our trans-Atlantic links in both defence and trade.</PARA><PARA>Dear friends, let us leave this hemicycle today with a clear resolve: to strengthen our Union, to secure our borders and to support our friends in need with more than just words. Our actions today will define the legacy of our generation and shape the course of history. The time for action is now.</PARA><PARA>Thank you.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-058-0000" PRE="3-057-0000" SUIV="3-059-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:02:29.368" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:06:56.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="AU NOM DU GROUPE"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="28229" CODICT="28229" LIB="Manfred | Weber" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Manfred Weber, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">on behalf of the PPE Group</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Madam President, Madam Vice-President, dear Prime Minister, dear Petteri, first of all, thank you for addressing the European Parliament and as an EPP Group leader, I want to congratulate you for the trust you received from the Finnish people for being elected as Prime Minister and after your success, Alexander Stubb was elected as President of Finland. So it is in good safe EPP hands today, thanks to the trust of the Finnish people.</PARA><PARA>Finland is a true EPP – European – success story, and also an EPP success story. The first country in Europe to introduce a universal election law for parliamentary elections in ‘96. In ‘97, when women had no voting rights in most of Europe, they were already 19 members in the Finnish Parliament – women, female members – in the Finnish Parliament. Since gaining independence in 1917, Finland has made an incredible journey: from being one of the poorest countries in Europe, it has become one of the most successful. And today, Finland is a European leader in gender equality, climate policy and innovation. Probably it has something to do with ‘sisu’, the special determination that defines the Finnish national character.</PARA><PARA>And, dear Petteri, you and Kokoomus have definitely shown some special determination in always standing up for Finland’s accession to NATO. The Finnish Socialists and Greens changed their minds about joining NATO only after the invasion of Ukraine, while already in 2018, you were warning Europe, I quote: ‘The crisis in Ukraine, recent terrorist attacks and hybrid threats have shown that both the EU’s defence cooperation and NATO are needed and that they can complement each other.’ And that is really true EPP leadership. </PARA><PARA>Finland makes both NATO and the European defence stronger. Not only do you bring the strongest artillery in Western Europe, an army capable of fighting in -40 degrees, but also the experience of guarding Europe’s longest border with Russia. Finns know what it means to have Russians as neighbours. Like the Ukrainians, you fought in cold trenches and frozen forests to stay free. The only difference is that you stood up to Stalin alone, whereas today we stand together against Putin.</PARA><PARA>This means not only supporting Ukraine as long as this takes, but also stopping Putin’s hybrid warfare against the Finnish border, as you said. Finland also is currently building up a fence to protect our external border. We, as the EPP do what is necessary to do and, dear Petteri, the Finnish border is a European border, as you said. The Finnish border is NATO border. No dictator can use illegal migration as a weapon to blackmail us as Europeans.</PARA><PARA>Standing together always means to build up also a competitive Europe. And when it comes to innovation, the Finns are hard to beat. Finland is today a world leader in digital infrastructure, the first country in Europe to build up a 5G network and it is already ready to implement 6G. Finland, Europe’s forest, has made innovation the basis of its climate policy. Companies are investing currently EUR 200 billion, 70 % of Finland’s GDP, in our green transition. Almost 1 in 3 Finnish employees works directly or indirectly in the tech sector. So you are proving that innovation is the way to more, to better quality jobs. And how do we do so? High quality education, investment and research and development for more than 3 % of GDP and cutting red tape. To become more innovative, Europe must become more like Finland.</PARA><PARA>Dear Petteri, your leadership is making Europe stronger, safer and ready to face not only today’s challenges, but also tomorrow’s challenges. Thank you for being with us.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-059-0000" PRE="3-058-0000" SUIV="3-060-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:07:05.583" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:11:58.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="AU NOM DU GROUPE"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="EN" MEPID="28298" CODICT="28298" LIB="Iratxe | García Pérez" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Iratxe García Pérez, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">on behalf of the S&amp;D Group</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Madam President, dear Prime Minister, welcome to the European Parliament. Welcome to the House of the European democracy.</PARA><PARA>The European people learned through great suffering that hate and fear are dangerous to democracy, a hate and fear that the far right has against those who they consider to be different, a hate and fear that are affecting the centre right within the European Union, where the far right has been allowed to be part of five national governments and hundreds of regional and municipal governments.</PARA><PARA>Dear Members, Finland is another example of the regression and the decline represented by the alliance between the European People’s Party and the far right. Mr Orpo, do you believe that the best way to defend workers’ rights is to promote dismissals, undermine social dialogue and restrict the right to strike? Do you think that the best way to eradicate poverty and inequality is to reduce public spending on pensions, unemployment benefits, housing and parental allowances?</PARA><PARA>Are you proud of your Finance Minister when she posts on social media with large scissors, expressing satisfaction at cutting people’s income and social security? Do you feel comfortable governing with a minister who declared himself a Nazi? And this person is still a minister.</PARA><PARA>Mr Orpo, your alliance with the far right is the real threat to our democracy and to the European project. This is why the future of the European Union is at stake. And the question that we must ask our citizens is clear. What kind of Europe do we want?</PARA><PARA>A Europe hostage to climate change denial or a Europe committed to fight against it and that makes the green transition an opportunity to create wealth? A Europe that undermines the sexual and reproductive health and rights of women or a Europe that defends the feminist cause and the achievements of women? A Europe of the elites or a Europe that protects workers in the face of the challenges posed by artificial intelligence and protects families in time of crisis, as we did during the pandemic on the war?</PARA><PARA>Dear Members, in times of uncertainty and great transformation, it is not enough to simply try to resist the reactionary wave. We have to move forward. We need a European project that makes citizens proud again to be European, a project that is not guided by the fear, hate and pessimism of the right and the far right.</PARA><PARA>Mr Orpo, Mr Weber, put an end to your alliance with those who want to destroy Europe. Let us continue building a Union that will be a beacon to inspire the world through its example of integration and progress; a Union with more democracy and more equality; a Union that makes the social pillar a reality with decent jobs and affordable housing; a Union that is more united and also more open; a Union at the forefront of the fight against climate change, committed to human rights, and that places people at the centre of the digital transformation.</PARA><PARA>Mr Orpo, Mr Weber, your only enemy is the far right. In the last century, your political family made a mistake by opening the door to the far right, and Europe and the world paid a high price. Now, let us say no to the darkness and yes to more years of hope and progress.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-060-0000" PRE="3-059-0000" SUIV="3-061-0000" VL="FR" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:12:04.843" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:14:31.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="AU NOM DU GROUPE"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="Renew" LG="FR" MEPID="135511" CODICT="135511" LIB="Valérie | Hayer" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Valérie Hayer, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">au nom du groupe Renew</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Madame la Présidente, Madame la Vice-Présidente, Monsieur le Premier Ministre, beaucoup, dans cet hémicycle, ont toujours considéré la Finlande, votre pays, comme une terre où règnent quiétude et sérénité. À tel point que nombreux sont ceux qui ont oublié que la Finlande partage la plus longue frontière d’Europe avec la Russie. Une frontière qui a été, vous l’avez rappelé, le théâtre d’une guerre hybride avec l’instrumentalisation de migrants, l’hiver dernier, par Vladimir Poutine. Avec l’arrivée du printemps, il y a fort à parier que cela soit de nouveau bientôt le cas.</PARA><PARA>C’est inacceptable, et l’Union européenne doit continuer à apporter le soutien nécessaire, comme elle a déjà commencé à le faire en mobilisant les agents de Frontex. Quelles que soient les manœuvres de Vladimir Poutine, nous nous y opposerons. Nous nous y opposerons, comme nous nous opposons à sa propagande – propagande qui voudrait faire croire que l’OTAN serait une force s’étendant tel un empire pour encercler la Russie. C’est un mensonge, et l’adhésion de la Finlande à l’OTAN en est une nouvelle preuve. Ce n’est pas l’OTAN qui s’étend d’elle-même, ce sont des États souverains qui font le choix, démocratiquement, de demander à rejoindre notre alliance. Pas l’inverse. </PARA><PARA>Si de nouveaux États souhaitent rejoindre l’OTAN, ce n’est évidemment pas par hasard. C’est parce qu’ils comprennent que le monde a évolué et que la Russie les menace à un tel point qu’ils sont prêts à renoncer à une politique de neutralité ancrée depuis des décennies dans leur identité politique.</PARA><PARA>Monsieur le Premier Ministre, chers collègues, tout cela démontre que la Finlande a sa place dans le réveil stratégique de l’Europe. Et pour cela, l’Union européenne doit muscler sa politique pour l’Arctique, où les intérêts des Américains, des Chinois ou des Russes sont grandissants. Des acteurs, disons-le, qui ne fondent pas nécessairement les mêmes espoirs que les Européens dans cette aire.</PARA><PARA>C’est pourquoi il nous faut une véritable stratégie, qui s’empare non seulement de la protection du climat et de la biodiversité dans la région, mais aussi des enjeux de défense et de diplomatie qui s’y jouent. C’est désormais un impératif géopolitique, pour la Finlande, pour toutes ces régions et pour l’Europe.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-061-0000" PRE="3-060-0000" SUIV="3-062-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:14:37.478" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:17:55.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="AU NOM DU GROUPE"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="Verts/ALE" LG="EN" MEPID="96648" CODICT="96648" LIB="Philippe | Lamberts" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Philippe Lamberts, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Madam President, dear Prime Minister, welcome to the European Parliament. It is pleasure to have you here.</PARA><PARA>As a leader of the Greens, you can imagine that I was expecting what you would say on the climate. I had to wait for a while in your speech to get to that point, and the first thing that struck me is that there was a lot in your speech about competitiveness, at the beginning, and then some stuff on the climate, and you don’t make the link. But this is the only game in town for Europe. If we do not lead this transition, China and the US will. So it is a matter of economic survival for Europe. It is not a detail of something that we can leave for later.</PARA><PARA>Second: details. You say that we focussed on details. Setting ourselves the goal of climate neutrality – a detail? Regulations to reduce emissions in transport, in buildings, in energy – details? Absolutely not! What we did is focus on the bare essentials.</PARA><PARA>There’s one point I agree with you on, which is that no, you cannot achieve everything through regulation. There I totally agree. But regulation sets ourselves targets and creates markets. So we need regulation. You cannot say okay, we should dispense with it. You didn’t say that, but you cannot at the same time say we need more carrots, but then we don’t want to spend money on it. I mean, what are the carrots if it is not public money?</PARA><PARA>There again I see really a contradiction in doing it. If we don’t want to do it through regulation, it is going to be subsidies. That’s what the US are doing. That’s what’s China is doing. They do not do anything on regulation; they do everything on subsidies. We have a more balanced approach where we have both regulation – say ‘sticks’ – and subsidies, and that’s ‘carrots’. But if you say we need less regulation and we want less state aid, and at the same time you say we want more climate action, then something is wrong. It doesn’t work. You can’t have all this.</PARA><PARA>Every study that looks at investment says we need between 2% and 2.5% of GDP extra on investment if we want to reach our climate targets. Of this, most agree that at least half should be public investment. There is no way around this. So this is a moment where we need to step up the public investment. Again, I would call on you to support these investments locally and at the European level rather than oppose them.</PARA><PARA>Finally, Prime Minister, you know, I disagree with Manfred Weber on a lot of things. I disagree with Valérie Hayer on a lot of things. I disagree with Iratxe García on a lot of things, and with the far left as well. But at least we have a common base. We have a common base, and that is that human dignity is indivisible. None of us says that some human beings are inferior or implies this. And this is where I believe that people like us should never, never go into alliance with people who de facto consider some human beings as inferior. That’s what you did in Finland. I’m glad, Manfred, that your colleagues in Portugal are not going to do that.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-062-0000" PRE="3-061-0000" SUIV="3-063-0000" VL="IT" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:18:01.158" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:20:05.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="AU NOM DU GROUPE"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="ECR" LG="IT" MEPID="197820" CODICT="197820" LIB="Nicola | Procaccini" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Nicola Procaccini, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">a nome del gruppo ECR</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Signora Presidente, signor primo ministro Orpo, è un grande piacere darLe il benvenuto a nome dei Conservatori europei.</PARA><PARA>Vista da qui, la vostra vittoria alle elezioni in Finlandia è stata più importante di quanto Lei possa immaginare; lei ha sconfitto la stella nascente dei socialisti europei, una delle massime esponenti delle follie <EMPHAS NAME="I">eurogreen</EMPHAS>, un&apos;icona dell&apos;agenda progressista globale, e questa cosa non gliela perdoneranno mai.</PARA><PARA>Ed ancora più significativa è stata la scelta di governare insieme al partito dei Finlandesi, autorevole membro della nostra famiglia politica; è riuscito a resistere alla pressione di chi non voleva l&apos;unione tra una forza politica del PPE ed una dell&apos;ECR, perché se il centrodestra è unito vince, ovunque in Europa, e questo le sinistre lo sanno bene. </PARA><PARA>Purtroppo talvolta riescono ancora a dividerci. Ricorda le parole di Paavo Haavikko? &quot;Quando le decisioni sono importanti, non tutti sono in grado di prenderle&quot;. Fortunatamente le sinistre non ce l&apos;hanno fatta a Praga, a Stoccolma, a Roma e a Helsinki.</PARA><PARA>E i fatti ci dicono che il vostro governo sta rilanciando l&apos;economia, diminuendo la burocrazia, difendendo la famiglia e preservando le tradizioni nazionali. Avete un approccio fermo e pragmatico sull&apos;immigrazione e avete compiuto la storica scelta di aderire alla NATO, rafforzando la nostra sicurezza comune in uno dei confini più difficili del nostro continente e della nostra libertà. <EMPHAS NAME="I">This is Europe</EMPHAS>! Questa è l&apos;Europa che amiamo e per cui vale la pena battersi! Buon lavoro.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-063-0000" PRE="3-062-0000" SUIV="3-065-0000" VL="FI" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:20:08.919" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:22:56.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="AU NOM DU GROUPE"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="ID" LG="FI" MEPID="197493" CODICT="197493" LIB="Jaak | Madison" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>FI</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jaak Madison, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">ID-ryhmän puolesta</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Arvoisa puhemies, hyvät kollegat, arvoisa pääministeri Orpo, olen oikein iloinen, että minulla on mahdollisuus puhua täällä virolaisena eli Suomen naapurimaan edustajana, joka on kulttuurisesti, historiallisesti ja kielellisesti lähellä Suomea. </PARA><PARA>Ensinnäkin ei voida korostaa liikaa sitä, kuinka tärkeää Suomen liittyminen Natoon on ollut Pohjois- ja Itä-Euroopalle ja kuinka tärkeää se on Virolle. Suomi on rakentanut puolustuskykyään vuosikymmeniä ja menestyksekkäästi, sillä Suomen puolustuskyky on yksi Euroopan parhaista. Virolaisena minulla on selvä käsitys, että Suomi on noudattanut periaatetta ”vähemmän sanoja, enemmän tekoja”. Muiden Euroopan maiden, myös Viron, tulisi noudattaa samaa. Nyt kun Viro ja Suomi ovat liittolaisia Natossa, se vahvistaa entisestään maidemme välistä yhteistyötä. Tiedämme hyvin historiasta, että yhteinen naapurimme Venäjä aina odottaa hetkeä, jolloin sen rajanaapurit ovat heikkoja ja unohtaneet Venäjän todellisen luonteen. </PARA><PARA>Mutta jotta sekä Viro että Suomi olisivat vahvoja, tarvitaan yhteistyötä, yhteistyötä myös Euroopan unionissa, koska monet Euroopan maat eivät ehkä ymmärrä tarpeeksi hyvin meille maissamme tärkeitä huolenaiheita. Esimerkiksi niin sanottu vihreä siirtymä: esimerkiksi riittävä energiansaanti on elintärkeää sekä Virolle että Suomelle, mutta sitä ei voida taata vain tuulella tai aurinkovoimalla, koska se on teknisesti mahdotonta, puhumattakaan valtavista summista, joita viherintoilijat ovat valmiita tuhlaamaan tähän tarkoitukseen ja joiden takia asukkaidemme toimeentulo heikkenee. Euroopassa pitäisi siirtyä realistiseen ilmasto- ja energiapolitiikkaan ja unohtaa vihreät utopiat. </PARA><PARA>Tämä koskee myös maahanmuuttopolitiikkaa. Vaikka Suomen väkiluku on lähes viisi kertaa suurempi kuin Viron, olemme silti pieniä maita sekä eurooppalaisessa että globaalissa mielessä. Maahanmuutto Lähi-idästä ja Afrikasta uhkaa kansallista olemassaoloamme. Emme voi unohtaa, että myös naapurimaamme Venäjä on käyttänyt maahanmuuttoa rajoillamme välineenä hybridihyökkäyksissä. Ongelmana on myös Euroopan unionin painostus yhteisen maahanmuuttopolitiikan harjoittamiseen, joka selvästi vaikeuttaa maidemme mahdollisuuksia hallita maahanmuuttoa. </PARA><PARA>Siksi toivon Suomen ja Viron yhteistyön lisääntyvän entisestään, koska huolemme myrskyisessä maailmassa ovat hyvin samankaltaisia. </PARA><PARA>And for the final statement, don’t very much listen about the Socialists and Greens because they haven’t really heard about democracy, that there are elections, and the people are giving the voice which kind of government they would like to have. That’s why good luck and keep on the same track.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-065-0000" PRE="3-063-0000" SUIV="3-066-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:23:01.459" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:26:18.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="AU NOM DU GROUPE"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="The Left" LG="EN" MEPID="197571" CODICT="197571" LIB="Nikolaj | Villumsen" SPEAKER_TYPE="au nom du groupe"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Nikolaj Villumsen, </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">on behalf of The Left Group</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Madam President, dear Mr Orpo, normally I would be happy and proud to welcome a prime minister from another Nordic country here in the European Parliament, but sadly I have to say today I’m not. Instead, I am disappointed, sad and honestly angry to have to welcome a Nordic prime minister that is leading a charge against social and trade union rights in his own country.</PARA><PARA>Mr Prime Minister, the topic today is ‘This is Europe’, and I have one thing to tell you: the Europe you represent, Mr Orpo, is not the Europe I want. And more importantly, it is definitely not the Europe citizens need. What you are doing is clearly wrong because you are undermining what makes a Nordic welfare state strong. Your government makes it easier to fire people, and at the same time you want to cut social welfare and protection. This will harm workers and their families.</PARA><PARA>Yet sadly it doesn’t stop here. At the same time, you try to undermine the Finnish system of collective bargaining – a collective bargaining system we, on a European level, aim to increase, you are actively trying to suppress. I’m sad to say so, but that is shameful.</PARA><PARA>As if this was not enough, you also want to limit the freedom of people to go on strike and protest your policies. But Prime Minister, when Finnish people protest you in the street, the solution is not to take away the possibility to strike. Instead you should stop, reflect and listen.</PARA><PARA>Mr Orpo, the Europe you represent is clearly a Europe for the few; a Europe that does not take care of your citizens, of our citizens and the planet. Instead, it runs away from responsibility. Sadly, we have seen it before. Whenever the right governs with the far right, the picture is the same. Those that claim to speak for the common man quickly betray him. Those that say they have the ordinary worker’s interests and concerns at heart quickly and brutally betray her. And that is exactly what is happening in Finland. That is exactly what we are seeing right now. And that is the reason that people are protesting you and your government, Mr Prime Minister.</PARA><PARA>Dear Mr Orpo, this is Europe, and what you provide is definitely not the Europe we want. Mr Orpo, this is Europe. It should be a Europe for the many, not just a Europe for the wealthy few.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-066-0000" PRE="3-065-0000" SUIV="3-067-0000" VL="FI" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:26:25.525" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:28:43.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="PPE" LG="FI" MEPID="40599" CODICT="40599" LIB="Sirpa | Pietikäinen"><LG>FI</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Sirpa Pietikäinen (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Arvoisa pääministeri, totesitte, että me tarvitsemme Euroopan, jolla on kyky toimia eikä vain reagoida. Kaikkea onnea ja rohkeutta sen tavoitteen eteenpäin viemiseksi neuvostossa, sillä sitä me juuri tarvitsemme tällä hetkellä. Eurooppa ei koskaan enää saa tulla yllätetyksi. Me tarvitsemme valmiusunionia, joka perustuu laajan turvallisuuden käsitykseen – olipa sitten kyse pandemioiden torjumisesta, lääkkeiden riittävyydestä, ruoan riittävyydestä ja laadusta, syliin kaatuvan ilmastonmuutoksen riittävästä torjunnasta ja kunnianhimon tason nostamisesta tai sitten valmiudesta sotilaallisiin epävarmuuksiin tai muunlaisiin hyökkäyksiin ympärillämme. </PARA><PARA>Me tarvitsemme laajan turvallisuuden käsitystä, joka ottaa myös, kuten sanoitte, sosiaalisen turvallisuuden mukaan. Sillä demokratian rapautuessa ja ääriliikkeiden noustessa myös toimintakykymme halvautuu, ja se voi olla tosiasiassa pahin uhka, joka meille voisi tapahtua. </PARA><PARA>Meillä pitää olla kykyä muuttaa ongelmat haasteiksi ja haasteet mahdollisuudeksi, ja juuri sitä on investointiunioni: se, miten transformoimme taloutemme ja teollisuutemme vihreäksi, kilpailukykyiseksi, informaatioteknologiaa hyväksikäyttäväksi ja kestävyyttä pitkällä aikajänteellä sekä sosiaalisesti että taloudellisesti tuottavaksi. Ja tähän meillä on kyky Euroopassa, paras mahdollinen globaalisti katsottuna. Tartutaan siihen kaksin käsin. Siirretään rahat siihen, mikä on tehokasta kilpailukykyistä tuotantoa, kasvatetaan kansallisvarallisuutta ja pidetään eurooppalaista huolta. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-067-0000" PRE="3-066-0000" SUIV="3-068-0000" VL="FI" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:28:47.398" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:30:01.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="FI" MEPID="197800" CODICT="197800" LIB="Eero | Heinäluoma"><LG>FI</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Eero Heinäluoma (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Hyvä nähdä teidät, pääministeri Orpo, täällä Euroopan parlamentissa. Suomi on täällä ollut aina arvostettu, rakentava jäsenmaa. Esittelitte ajatuksia varautumisunionista. Hyvä niin. Mutta entä sosiaalinen unioni, ihmisiä puolustava unioni, kaikkien markkinavoimien keskellä? Tästähän Delors puhui: työmarkkinoiden sopimustoiminnan edistämisestä, vuoropuhelusta, yhdessä tekemisestä, toistensa kunnioittamisesta. Eikö teidän pitäisi viedä eteenpäin yritysvastuudirektiiviä, kunnioittaa naisten oikeuksia, työntekijöiden ja kuluttajien oikeuksia suurten monikansallisten yritysten puristuksessa? Eikö pitäisi viedä eteenpäin luontokadon pysäyttävää lainsäädäntöä? </PARA><PARA>Eurooppaa rakennetaan positiivisin aloitteen. Siksi toivonkin, että hallituksenne vie eteenpäin sosiaalisesti kestävää unionia, mutta olisi aloitteellinen myös puolustusyhteistyössä. Eikö olisi aika nostaa suomalainen EU:n ensimmäiseksi puolustuskomissaariksi? </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-068-0000" PRE="3-067-0000" SUIV="3-069-0000" VL="FI" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:30:03.102" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:32:23.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="Renew" LG="FI" MEPID="197563" CODICT="197563" LIB="Mauri | Pekkarinen"><LG>FI</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Mauri Pekkarinen (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Arvoisa puhemies, herra pääministeri, EU:n keskeinen peruspilari ovat reilut sisämarkkinat. Ne ovat erityisen tärkeät viennistä elävälle maalle, kuten Suomelle. Reiluus tarkoittaa sitä, että yritykset kilpailevat sisämarkkinoilla aidosti ja kilpailukykyisimmät voittavat. Se takaa koko EU:n tuottavuuden ja kasvun. Komission syksystä 2020 lähtien myöntämät neljän tuhannen miljardin euron suuruiset poikkeukset valtiontukisääntöihin rikkovat tätä periaatetta. Miljardien käyttäminen milloin suurten yritysten hankintaan omaan maahan, milloin vaikkapa fossiilisen energian tukemiseen – tämä kaikki on väärin. Kiitos pääministeri Orpo, että tuomitsitte tämän. Näin ymmärsin. </PARA><PARA>EU:n talouskehitys on surkeaa. Kun kasvun tekijöistä työpanoksen määrä ei juurikaan EU:ssa lisäänny, tuottavuuden parantamiseksi on nyt kyettävä ottamaan pitkä loikka. Siihen tarvitaan rahaa. Olin aikanaan tekemässä kuuluisaa päätöstä, että EU:n pitää saavuttaa 2020 kolmen prosentin taso tutkimus- ja innovaatiorahoituksessa. Me olemme epäonnistuneet surkeasti tässä. EU:ssa kuitenkin käytetään alue- ja elvytystukiin yhteensä varoja noin tuhannen miljardin euron verran muutamassa vuodessa. Näille rahoille on osoitettava uusi suunta: tutkimuksen, innovaatioiden ja avainteknologioiden tukemisen suunta. Ja se on ihan muuta kuin sisämarkkinoita rapauttava valtion tuki. </PARA><PARA>Putinin julma sota on suuri inhimillinen katastrofi, mutta se on myös iso aineellinen menetys Venäjän ja Valko-Venäjän naapureille. EU:n Interreg-ohjelma on hyvä auttamaan ystävällismielisten rajanaapureiden yhteistyötä. Nyt Venäjä ei ole ystävällismielinen eikä Interreg auta EU:n itärajan maakuntia. EU tarvitsee siksi nyt uuden ulkorajaohjelman. Sellaisen tarve on valtavan paljon suurempi ja perustellumpi kuin brexitin vuoksi ulkorajanaapureille annettu 5 miljardin euron tuki. </PARA><PARA>Tärkeä osa EU:n strategisen autonomian ja huoltovarmuuden varmistamista on metsien kestävä käyttö. Mikään muu kuin puu ei voi korvata uusiutumattomia raaka-aineita. </PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Puhuja suostuu vastaamaan sinisen kortin puheenvuoroon)</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-069-0000" PRE="3-068-0000" SUIV="3-070-0000" VL="RO" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:32:47.470" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:34:37.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="QUESTION &quot;CARTON BLEU&quot;"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="RO" MEPID="124785" CODICT="124785" LIB="Maria | Grapini" SPEAKER_TYPE="question  carton bleu "><LG>RO</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Maria Grapini (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">întrebare adresată conform procedurii „cartonașului albastru”</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Domnul prim-ministru a spus aici de mai multe ori: „trebuie, trebuie, trebuie”. Vreau să vă întreb dacă, din ceea ce a prezentat aici prim-ministrul, dumneavoastră ați înțeles că noi avem oportunități egale, toți, în Uniunea Europeană acum? Având în vedere că domnul prim-ministru a fost și ministru al agriculturii <EMPHAS NAME="I">(vorbitoarea este întreruptă din motive tehnice).</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>Vă întreb, domnul prim-ministru a folosit de mai multe ori cuvântul „trebuie” <EMPHAS NAME="I">(vorbitoarea este întreruptă din motive tehnice).</EMPHAS></PARA><PARA>Domnul prim-ministru a spus de mai multe ori în intervenția domniei sale că „trebuie și trebuie și trebuie”. O să mă leg de o frază, și anume că este nevoie să avem oportunități egale, toți, în Uniunea Europeană, adică toți cetățenii din cele 27 de țări.</PARA><PARA>Considerați că, prin ceea ce a spus domnul prim-ministru, acum avem oportunități egale? Domnul prim-ministru este și membru al Consiliului și fost ministru al agriculturii, și întreb: cum consideră că ar trebui modificat PAC-ul pentru a fi egalitate pentru fermierii din Uniunea Europeană? Cum ar trebui să pledeze pentru Schengen ca să avem o piață unică?</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-070-0000" PRE="3-069-0000" SUIV="3-071-0000" VL="FI" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:34:33.420" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:36:00.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="RÉPONSE &quot;CARTON BLEU&quot;"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="Renew" LG="FI" MEPID="197563" CODICT="197563" LIB="Mauri | Pekkarinen" SPEAKER_TYPE="reponse  carton bleu "><LG>FI</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Mauri Pekkarinen (<PP>Renew</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">vastaus sinisen kortin kysymykseen</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – En aivan tarkkaan kuullut kysymyksen alkuosaa, mutta ymmärsin, että kysymyksen ydin liittyy kuitenkin siihen, että miten yhteistä maatalouspolitiikkaa pitäisi uudistaa, jotta kaikkialla Euroopan unionissa viljelijöillä olisi samanlaiset edellytykset. Se on tärkeä kysymys ja mielestäni todellakaan tänään se ei tapahdu. YMP ei vastaa eri puolilla Eurooppaa olevaa todellisuutta maatalouden harjoittamisen edellytyksistä. Kun minä katson täällä ympärilleni, kun asun täällä Strasbourgissa, täällä on vihreät pellot. Kun minä menen kotiin, siellä on metri lunta. Näiden peltojen hehtaarikohtainen tuki YMP:ssä on suurin piirtein sama teillä Ranskassa kuin meillä Suomessa. Tässä yksi esimerkki siitä, millä tavalla nykyinen YMP ei käsittele oikeudenmukaisesti ja tasapuolisesti kaikkia Euroopan unionin jäsenmaita. Muutenkaan YMP ei ehkä tunnista sitä totuutta, että ilmastonmuutos on iso tosiasia ja se heijastaa monella tavalla uudentyyppisiä haasteita yhteiselle maatalouspolitiikalle. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-071-0000" PRE="3-070-0000" SUIV="3-072-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:35:49.932" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:37:20.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="Verts/ALE" LG="EN" MEPID="197802" CODICT="197802" LIB="Ville | Niinistö"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Ville Niinistö (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Madam President, I do appreciate the way our Prime Minister spoke about European defence and the need to support Ukraine. On that, we Finns are united. Europe needs to lift itself in order to stop Putin’s war policy and his policy of aggression. </PARA><PARA>However, our Prime Minister is a man of softly spoken words. He says, for example, that he wants to build on the Nordic labour model in Finland, when his actions are actually dismantling it. He says that he wants to keep the Finnish carbon neutrality target, when they do no action to achieve it, neither when it comes to forest sinks or reducing emissions or promoting CCS that he says that they would like to promote. They just don’t do it. </PARA><PARA>At the same time, he gave an interview to <EMPHAS NAME="I">Politico</EMPHAS> last week about the far right Finns Party in your government, and you said that you have ‘moderated’ them by giving them ministerial posts. They are not far right anymore, you said. </PARA><PARA>Well my question is, what party actually has changed in this government when Finland is facing unprecedented, historical strikes larger than in decades, with your labour cuts and your cuts on welfare, where a middle-income earner who becomes unemployed, a women with two children, can lose over EUR 500 a month? </PARA><PARA>Which party has changed? Have you moderated the far right, or have you yourself moved further to the right to legitimise anti-egalitarian, anti-climate policies that are dismantling the Nordic labour model? That is the question that you have to answer. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-072-0000" PRE="3-071-0000" SUIV="3-073-0000" VL="FI" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:37:30.481" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:40:12.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="ECR" LG="FI" MEPID="132366" CODICT="132366" LIB="Pirkko | Ruohonen-Lerner"><LG>FI</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Pirkko Ruohonen-Lerner (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Arvoisa puhemies, omalta osaltani haluan myös toivottaa teidät, pääministeri Orpo, tervetulleeksi Euroopan parlamenttiin. Haluan näin kärkeen korjata myös sosialistien ryhmäpuheen karkeudet, ja totean, että Suomessa ei ole äärioikeistopuoluetta hallituksessa. Meillä on isänmaallinen hallitus, joka tekee parhaansa korjatakseen edellisen sosialistihallituksen katastrofaalisen perinnön ja jättämän suunnattoman velkataakan, jota ei voida hoitaa ottamalla aina lisää ja lisää uutta velkaa ja jatkamalla holtitonta taloudenpitoa. </PARA><PARA>Viime syksynä Venäjä aloitti hybridioperaation Suomen rajalla käyttäen siirtolaisia aseena. Suomen hallitus toimi asiassa erittäin päättäväisesti sulkiessaan koko itärajan. Brutaalia hyökkäyssotaa kolmatta vuotta käyvä Venäjä on äärimmäisen arvaamaton. Kaikkiin mahdollisiin skenaarioihin on syytä varautua. Laittomien maahantulijoiden rajanylitykset on estettävä, tarvittaessa voimakeinoin. On muistettava, että Suomen rajavartijat turvaavat koko EU:n yhteistä ulkorajaa. </PARA><PARA>Tukea Ukrainalle on jatkettava ja entisestään voimistettava. Ukrainan on voitettava tämä sota, ja on velvollisuutemme tehdä kaikkemme, jotta tämä tavoite saavutetaan. </PARA><PARA>Vastuullinen taloudenpito on tärkeää koko EU:ssa ja kaikissa sen jäsenmaissa. Yli varojen ei voi elää. Suomi ei ensimmäistä kertaa historiassaan tukenut vastuuvapauden myöntämistä Euroopan komissiolle, mistä nostan hattua. Päätöksen taustalla olivat EU:n tilintarkastustuomioistuimen huolestuttavat havainnot EU-budjetin menojen hallinnan olennaisista ja laajalle levinneistä virheistä. </PARA><PARA>Euroopan talouden kilpailukyvystä on pidettävä huolta. On välttämätöntä, että Suomen talous saadaan jälleen oikeille urille. Toivonkin johtamaltanne hallitukselta päättäväisyyttä poliittisten lakkojen edessä. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-073-0000" PRE="3-072-0000" SUIV="3-074-0000" VL="FR" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:40:19.811" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:42:05.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="ID" LG="FR" MEPID="131580" CODICT="131580" LIB="Jordan | Bardella"><LG>FR</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Jordan Bardella (<PP>ID</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Premier ministre, alors que notre continent est agité par des tensions géopolitiques majeures et par le retour de la guerre, je veux vous parler des factures d’énergie, qui continuent d’augmenter mois après mois, pénalisant tout autant des fins de mois difficiles que la compétitivité de notre économie. L’Europe est-elle condamnée à voir ses usines partir et ses producteurs mourir? Cette question terrible, tous les Européens lucides se la posent. Les prix de l’énergie restent en effet l’un des plus grands handicaps pour notre continent, notamment face à l’Asie et aux États-Unis.</PARA><PARA>Depuis 2022, la hausse des prix de l’énergie a frappé de plein fouet nos boulangers, nos agriculteurs, nos industries, qui paient deux ans d’inaction pour résoudre cette urgence absolue. On juge la pertinence d’un modèle à sa résilience. Or, il faut voir en face l’échec de ce mécanisme européen de fixation des prix de l’énergie, qui n’a pas su protéger les peuples et les entreprises d’une explosion des tarifs. Il en a été l’amplificateur, diffusant l’onde de choc à toutes les composantes de notre économie, de l’industrie à l’agriculture en passant par les familles ou encore par nos boulangers.</PARA><PARA>En deux ans, l’Union européenne n’a pas été capable de réformer ce marché européen de l’électricité. Contrairement à certains, je ne me résous pas à ce grand déménagement industriel. Alors que la France dispose de l’atout historique du nucléaire, elle doit retrouver sa souveraineté énergétique dans une Europe qui investit enfin collectivement dans cette énergie abondante, bon marché et décarbonée. Le continent qui a vu naître Peugeot et Renault, le continent de la famille Dassault, le continent du Concorde, de l’Airbus ou du train à grande vitesse ne peut devenir un désert industriel. Ce serait une trahison du génie créatif de l’Europe.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-074-0000" PRE="3-073-0000" SUIV="3-075-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:42:10.531" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:44:11.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="124802" CODICT="124802" LIB="Siegfried | Mureşan"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Siegfried Mureşan (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Madam President, Prime Minister Orpo, welcome to the European Parliament. Thank you for a very pro-European speech, which is confirmed by your daily actions as Prime Minister. Finland is a model for many of us in many aspects. Finland is a model in terms of research and innovation, in terms of education, and Finland is globally a top-five country when it comes to defending the rule of law, fighting against corruption and defending the freedom of the press. And by the way, under the leadership of pro-European centre-right Prime Minister Petteri Orpo Finland is scoring better in defending European values than any country led by a left-wing government in Europe today.</PARA><PARA>We have many things to do together. Let me choose two: security and competitiveness, two topics which the Prime Minister has touched upon. In the area of security, to protect European citizens, we will have to do more than we anticipated initially. We will have to do it faster, earlier and for a longer period of time. We will have to pool our resources together to make sure that our troops are well equipped with the most modern, most effective equipment to be able to protect the people in Europe. Thank you very much, Prime Minister, for your readiness to have more European action in this area. And also thank you for protecting the Finnish border to the weaponised migration from the Russian Federation. Through your actions, you are protecting citizens everywhere in Europe. You are protecting a European border.</PARA><PARA>On competitiveness, we need a strong economy to be able to protect our citizens. We need a strong economy to be able to safeguard our social model in Europe. We all want pensions, minimum wages, all to be safeguarded and secured. In this respect, we will have to invest in research, innovation, digitisation, free trade, complete the single market, create a framework which the private sector feels comfortable to invest in.</PARA><PARA>Today we heard from Prime Minister Orpo that Europe can rely on Finland, and today we are telling to you, Prime Minister, that Finland can rely on the European Union.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-075-0000" PRE="3-074-0000" SUIV="3-076-0000" VL="SV" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:44:13.466" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:45:35.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="SV" MEPID="197391" CODICT="197391" LIB="Heléne | Fritzon"><LG>SV</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Heléne Fritzon (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Fru talman! Statsministern! Finland och Sverige har så mycket gemensamt, inte minst vår nordiska arbetsmarknadsmodell. Den nordiska modellen som bygger på dialog och förhandling mellan starka och jämbördiga parter. Den har varit en källa till stolthet, styrka och välstånd för våra länder.</PARA><PARA>Men det jag ser nu som pågår i Finland gör mig orolig. Attacker på föreningsrätten, på strejkrätten och på arbetsrätten. Jag hör också att civilsamhällesorganisationerna i Finland varnar för att regeringens planerade nedskärningar riskerar att putta nästan 17 000 barn under fattigdomsgränsen. Detta i en tid när många kämpar med höjda priser. </PARA><PARA>Både Finland och Sverige har regeringar som har valt att samarbeta med de högerextrema. Statsministern! Min uppmaning blir därför till er att i en orolig omvärld måste politiken skapa sammanhållning och samförstånd, inte splittring och konfrontation. </PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Talaren godtog att svara på ett inlägg (&quot;blått kort&quot;))</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-076-0000" PRE="3-075-0000" SUIV="3-078-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:45:44.363" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:46:40.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="QUESTION &quot;CARTON BLEU&quot;"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="112611" CODICT="112611" LIB="Petri | Sarvamaa" SPEAKER_TYPE="question  carton bleu "><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Petri Sarvamaa (<PP>PPE</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">blue-card question</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – First of all, I have to remind the honourable Members that when we had a socialist Prime Minister, our instruction to the EPP was not to make this a discussion about domestic politics.</PARA><PARA>Min fråga till er ärade Europaparlamentariker Fritzon är, varför gjorde ni exakt tvärtom här i dag? </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-078-0000" PRE="3-076-0000" SUIV="3-079-0000" VL="SV" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:46:37.754" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:47:18.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="RÉPONSE &quot;CARTON BLEU&quot;"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="SV" MEPID="197391" CODICT="197391" LIB="Heléne | Fritzon" SPEAKER_TYPE="reponse  carton bleu "><LG>SV</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Heléne Fritzon (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">svar (&quot;blått kort&quot;)</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Fru talman! Tack för frågan. Vi sitter i Europaparlamentet i en tid när vi har kris och krig i Europa. Varje medlemsstats agerande betyder en viktig skillnad för hur vårt samarbete fungerar. </PARA><PARA>Därför är det mycket relevant att påpeka att när samarbeten stärks i våra medlemsstater där vi tar in de högerextrema i regeringsarbetet, då öppnar vi också för att vi utmanar våra gemensamma europeiska demokratiska värden. Det är skälet till att jag pratar om det som pågår i Sverige och Finland. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-079-0000" PRE="3-078-0000" SUIV="3-080-0000" VL="FI" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:47:16.066" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:49:08.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="Renew" LG="FI" MEPID="114268" CODICT="114268" LIB="Nils | Torvalds"><LG>FI</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Nils Torvalds (<PP>Renew</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Arvoisa puhemies, arvoisa komission puheenjohtaja, hyvä Petteri, tämä talo on vähän kuin Baabelin torni. Onneksi meillä on tulkit, jotka tekevät sekavastakin puheesta melkein ymmärrettävää. Mutta tänä päivänä joudumme vähän heitä haastamaan. Suomen kieli tuntee sellaisen sanan kuin orpo olo. Ja minulle tulee orpo olo silloin, kun katson, miten Suomi ja Eurooppa pärjää kilpailussa. Me jäämme jatkuvasti jälkeen sekä Yhdysvalloista että Kiinasta. Eräs syy tähän on se, että meillä on hallinnollinen taakka, joka välillä on ylisuuri. </PARA><PARA>Siitä syystä meidän pitää nyt katsoa, mitä tapahtuu tulevaisuudessa, kun kaikki esittävät tällaisia joulupukin listoja seuraavalle komissiolle. Seuraavan komission tehtävä on aikaansaada raamilainsäädäntöä. Keskustellaan vähän ranskalaiseen tapaan, että nyt kirjoitetaan pitkiä listoja siitä, mitä pitää tehdä ja mitä ei saa tehdä. Mutta on olemassa raamilainsäädäntöä, jolla voidaan luoda suuntaviivoja ja vielä hallita tätä tulevaisuudessa. Mutta tämä puute synnyttää tämän orvon olon. Tämä orpo olo ei tietenkään ole mitenkään sukua meidän pääministerille, mutta en voinut vastustaa kiusausta vähän leikkiä sanoilla, koska se on meidän tehtävä. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-080-0000" PRE="3-079-0000" SUIV="3-081-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:49:11.207" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:50:28.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="Verts/ALE" LG="EN" MEPID="197453" CODICT="197453" LIB="Anna | Deparnay-Grunenberg"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Anna Deparnay-Grunenberg (<PP>Verts/ALE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Madam President, honourable Prime Minister Mr Orpo, dear colleagues, last October, Mr Orpo sent a letter to our President von der Leyen raising concerns about the pressure on forest and forestry due to EU legislation.</PARA><PARA>You asked to take more time. Already today, three quarters of Finland’s forest habitats are threatened. Already today, Finnish forests became a net emitter of carbon dioxide instead of a sink. And it’s not EU legislation that is responsible for the bad state of Finnish forests. </PARA><PARA>We cannot afford to take more time. To use your own words, we need a Union that acts, fighting the climate and biodiversity crisis together, and our European forests are our strongest allies in this fight. So I ask you today, what is your plan to improve the state of Finnish forests? How can Finland contribute to a successful monitoring law that is upcoming now? And when will the big clear cuts in Finland that are still practice in 80 % of the forest finally be stopped?</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-081-0000" PRE="3-080-0000" SUIV="3-082-0000" VL="PL" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:50:33.197" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:51:40.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="ECR" LG="PL" MEPID="124891" CODICT="124891" LIB="Zdzisław | Krasnodębski"><LG>PL</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Zdzisław Krasnodębski (<PP>ECR</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Premierze! W tamtym tygodniu odbyły się dni studyjne w Helsinkach (pięknym mieście) i podczas rozmów z politykami i ekspertami mogliśmy się przekonać, jak realistycznie podchodzi obecny rząd – i myślę, że Finowie w ogóle – do kwestii ochrony granic, migracji oraz do sprawy obrony i zagrożenia ze strony Rosji. Finlandia utrzymała obowiązek służby wojskowej wtedy, gdy zrezygnowano już z niego w większości krajów europejskich, co, jak wiemy, było błędem. Dzisiaj potrzebna jest realistyczna polityka obronna w Europie, to znaczy taka, która wzmacnia, a nie osłabia NATO. I pan premier o tym mówił. Nie osłabia się państw członkowskich i patriotyzmu ich obywateli mrzonkami o armii europejskiej i budowie państwa europejskiego. </PARA><PARA>Chciałem powiedzieć, że z przyjemnością wysłuchałem pełnego realizmu wystąpienia pana premiera, i mam nadzieję, że w tym kierunku będziemy zmierzać w przyszłej kadencji. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-082-0000" PRE="3-081-0000" SUIV="3-083-0000" VL="DA" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:51:44.188" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:52:51.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="ID" LG="DA" MEPID="124875" CODICT="124875" LIB="Anders | Vistisen"><LG>DA</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Anders Vistisen (<PP>ID</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Fru formand! Hr. premierminister! Ulovlig indvandring bruges som et våben mod de europæiske grænser. Vi har set det i Finland, hvor Rusland med deres aggression har skubbet ulovlige migranter mod dit land. Vi har set det i Middelhavet. Vi har set det i Tyrkiet mod Grækenland og Bulgarien, og det er noget, vi er nødt til at tage alvorligt fra Europas side. For selvfølgelig kan vi ikke forlade os på, at vores naboer altid har de bedste intentioner i sinde, når de bruger den slags instrumenter imod os. Derfor er det nødvendigt, at vi fra EU&apos;s side tager sagen i egen hånd og sørger for at løse udfordringen omkring den ulovlige migration én gang for alle her på vores kontinent og ikke regner med, at vi altid har venligtsindede naboer. For historien viser – som situationen i Rusland, i Tyrkiet og andre steder – at det kan vi ikke forlade os på. Lad os derfor tage det alvorligt nu, og lad os få gjort noget ved det, både i Finland og i resten af EU. </PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Taleren accepterede at besvare et blåt kort-indlæg)</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-083-0000" PRE="3-082-0000" SUIV="3-084-0000" VL="DA" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:53:04.324" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:53:29.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="QUESTION &quot;CARTON BLEU&quot;"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="DA" MEPID="101585" CODICT="101585" LIB="Niels | Fuglsang" SPEAKER_TYPE="question  carton bleu "><LG>DA</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Niels Fuglsang (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">Blåt-kort-spørgsmål</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Fru formand! Ja, det er meget interessant, Anders Vistisen, med din kritik af, at tingene ikke bliver taget alvorligt, og din kritik af EU og alle mulige andre. Den sang kender vi fra dig. Men hvad er dit eget forslag egentlig til, hvordan vi forbedrer tingene her? </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-084-0000" PRE="3-083-0000" SUIV="3-085-0000" VL="DA" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:53:29.533" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:54:22.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="RÉPONSE &quot;CARTON BLEU&quot;"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="ID" LG="DA" MEPID="124875" CODICT="124875" LIB="Anders | Vistisen" SPEAKER_TYPE="reponse  carton bleu "><LG>DA</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Anders Vistisen (<PP>ID</PP>), </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">Blåt-kort-svar</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Jamen, Dansk Folkepartis forslag er jo det forslag, som de danske socialdemokrater har kopieret. Det er den australske model, og jeg er jo glad for, at vi har inspireret socialdemokraterne i Danmark. Nu tilhører socialdemokraterne desværre her i S&amp;D-Gruppen et meget, meget lille mindretal, der ønsker at gøre noget ved den ulovlige indvandring. Men jeg synes da, der er god grund til at rose de danske socialdemokrater, og det er jo også derfor, mine kollegaer i AFD, i Rassemblement National og andre steder peger på Danmark, hvor Dansk Folkeparti har haft indflydelse på udlændingepolitikken, som et mønstereksempel på, hvor godt det kunne være i EU, hvis man gav højrefløjen indflydelse. Så tak til Niels Fuglsang for at demonstrere vigtigheden af den pointe. Jeg er glad for samarbejdet med de danske socialdemokrater, selv om I engang imellem er lidt for bløde til min smag. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-085-0000" PRE="3-084-0000" SUIV="3-086-0000" VL="SV" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:54:22.232" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:55:30.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="PPE" LG="SV" MEPID="197402" CODICT="197402" LIB="Tomas | Tobé"><LG>SV</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Tomas Tobé (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Fru talman! Statsminister Orpo Petteri. Finland är och förblir Sveriges närmaste partner. Ett partnerskap som nu blir ännu starkare då båda våra länder nu äntligen är medlemmar i Nato. Jag vill från djupet av mitt hjärta tacka dig och Finland för stödet under denna resa. <EMPHAS NAME="I">Kiitos</EMPHAS>. </PARA><PARA>Tyvärr är vi ju i en situation i Europa då vi har krig och båda våra länder har ju en central roll nu i att inte bara ge militärt och ekonomiskt stöd till Ukraina utan också, tror jag, i att vara glasklar i dessa tider att det inte är Ukraina som ska visa vit flagg, det är inte Ukraina som ska tvingas till förhandlingar utan det är Putin som ska ut ur Ukraina och Europa som ska försvaras. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-086-0000" PRE="3-085-0000" SUIV="3-087-0000" VL="IT" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:55:35.385" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:56:50.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="IT" MEPID="124867" CODICT="124867" LIB="Brando | Benifei"><LG>IT</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Brando Benifei (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Presidente Orpo, l&apos;idea di Europa che il suo governo rappresenta è l&apos;opposto di ciò di cui c&apos;è bisogno: un&apos;alleanza dove partiti sedicenti moderati ed europeisti si piegano alla destra nazionalista e reazionaria come il partito dei Veri Finlandesi.</PARA><PARA>Un modello che forse può piacere ai Meloni e Salvini d&apos;Europa, ma che produce solo divisione, debolezza, isolamento e fragilità per l&apos;Europa. Non dimentichiamo le affermazioni demenziali, razziste, omofobe del pluricondannato presidente del parlamento finlandese, senza contare la vicenda dell&apos;ex ministro dell&apos;Economia che si è dovuto dimettere per commenti filonazisti.</PARA><PARA>Non solo affermazioni, ma anche riforme distruttive come le vostre modifiche al mercato del lavoro e della sicurezza sociale, che hanno portato i lavoratori a protestare nelle strade per giorni. </PARA><PARA>Noi siamo contro queste ammucchiate dove sedicenti europeisti strizzano l&apos;occhio all&apos;estrema destra; vale in Italia e vale in Europa, dove alle prossime elezioni dovremo lavorare perché l&apos;Europa mantenga una strada chiara.</PARA><PARA>Presidente Orpo, non si faccia dettare l&apos;agenda dai Veri Finlandesi, dimostri, nell&apos;interesse dei finlandesi e degli europei, di essere un vero europeo.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-087-0000" PRE="3-086-0000" SUIV="3-088-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:56:53.271" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:58:14.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="PPE" LG="EN" MEPID="124726" CODICT="124726" LIB="Henna | Virkkunen"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Henna Virkkunen (<PP>PPE</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Madam President, Prime Minister Orpo, I wish to thank you, Prime Minister, for being here with us today, and thank you for your excellent speech.</PARA><PARA>The three main priorities you highlighted – strengthening Europe’s strategic competitiveness, improving our comprehensive security and promoting a clean transition – are precisely the sectors on which the European Union must focus. We must create a Europe that encourages companies to innovate and invest in Europe. We need to strengthen our own capacity, both in the economy and in security, so that Europe has the ability to act in all situations. </PARA><PARA>Finland is a good example of a model of comprehensive security where citizens, companies and the public sector work closely together to ensure preparedness, resilience and security of supply. Your proposal for a preparedness Union is indeed an excellent initiative that should be taken forward. </PARA><PARA>Prime Minister, I fully support your words about Ukraine. The European Union must bolster up our support for Ukraine. Concrete decisions and action is needed. We must help Ukraine win the war. </PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-088-0000" PRE="3-087-0000" SUIV="3-089-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T11:58:18.370" VOD-END="2024-03-13T11:59:57.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="S-D" LG="EN" MEPID="124735" CODICT="124735" LIB="Miapetra | Kumpula-Natri"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Miapetra Kumpula-Natri (<PP>S&amp;D</PP>).</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> – Madam President, first of all, there is no opposition here in Parliament. We are here for the different groups and for the citizens. I read the EPP promise for the next elections. It says it wants to defend workers’ rights and wants to have fair income. How do you, Petteri Orpo, take that EPP message to Council? And is this fake? We have people on the streets now. There are big strikes going on. The KOK Government is cutting benefits, cutting rights for the political strikes, and at the same time making benefits for our income level, the most rich one, and cutting the poor. And I am very worried that ‘17 000 more poor children’ is in the programme.</PARA><PARA>The previous government was in the time of the growing economy, and this government takes more loans than the previous one. So this is my call for the Council what to do: on the defence on the eastern border these issues are national and I welcome very much the strong words of the government that has to be taken there.</PARA><PARA>And finally, something was missing: the rule of law. You didn’t take that up. Is it because the MEPs here voted against your ministers and speakers, and others are saying that this is not important, it is Hungary who have their national rights? Please be strong there. The Finnish voice is needed. The processes started last term. They are vital for the democracy as well.</PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-089-0000" PRE="3-088-0000" SUIV="3-094-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T12:00:08.707" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:11.000" SPEAKER_TYPE="PRIME MINISTER OF FINLAND"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="0" CODICT="253625" LIB="Petteri | Orpo" SPEAKER_TYPE="prime minister of finland"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">Petteri Orpo,</EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA> <EMPHAS NAME="I">Prime Minister of Finland</EMPHAS><EMPHAS NAME="B">.</EMPHAS> – Madam President, thank you for your attention and contribution. Thank you for the excellent European and domestic debate. A few comments on your remarks.</PARA><PARA>First, Mr Weber, thank you for your strong support. On NATO, you mentioned it is important that today in Finland we are united. Almost all Members of Finland’s Parliament support our membership of NATO, and together in Finland we are building up a strong NATO in Finland at this moment, and I’m proud of it.</PARA><PARA>Ms García Pérez – and for many others also – there are no far-right parties in my government. The Finnish Government is pro-rule of law; it’s pro-democracy; it’s pro-equal gender rights; it’s pro-Ukraine; pro-European Union.</PARA><PARA>Many of you were worried about the reforms we are doing in Finland. But we have to do those reforms, because in 15 years our economy has not grown and we are going to lose our welfare in Finland. That is why we are reforming our economy. We are reforming the labour market, the social security system, taxation, because our target is to create 100 000 jobs for the Finnish people, so we can take care of all Finnish people and take care of our welfare state, education, healthcare, etc. This is clear.</PARA><PARA>Ms Hayer, thank you for your strong words on our common security. The Arctic is a very important issue.</PARA><PARA>Mr Lambert, thank you for your very wise words. There is a strong link between growth and climate. It is clear. The green transition will provide opportunities to our businesses. We do need regulation, but we need better regulation.</PARA><PARA>And I want to also mention that we use EUR 1 billion to develop and research more in this period, because we need new innovations because of climate.</PARA><PARA>Viro ja Suomi ovat hyvin läheiset naapurit, ja yhteistyömme Itämeren alueen turvallisuudessa, rajaturvallisuudessa, energiassa, monissa kysymyksissä ovat meille hyvin tärkeät. </PARA><PARA>Vi har ett fantastiskt samarbete med den svenska regeringen och vi har reformerat våra arbetsmarknader till den svenska modellen. </PARA><PARA>Eero Heinäluoman ehdotus ja tuki komission puheenjohtajan Von der Leyenin aloitteelle puolustuskomissaarista on erinomaisen hyvä, ja Suomi tukee sitä. </PARA><PARA>Dear colleagues, to my conclusions. My main messages for this Chamber are clear and urgent.</PARA><PARA>Firstly, we cannot afford to hesitate. The situation with Russia is not just a momentary crisis; it is a test of our resolve and our foresight. If we do not act decisively against the aggression now, we are effectively inviting future challenges to our borders and to the very ideals we hold dear. President Putin’s ambitions will not be curbed by inaction. He will be emboldened by it.</PARA><PARA>Secondly, time is of the essence. Our words must now be matched by tangible action. We need to accelerate our defence production capabilities immediately. All these efforts require time – time that is slipping through our fingers even as we speak. The time to act is now.</PARA><PARA>By working together, we can multiply our effectiveness. Naturally, bilateral help is needed, but the EU must also work collectively. The unity displayed by the European Union has been commendable. However, it is now imperative that we embark on the next phase of our collective journey. Our security cannot hinge on the outcomes of elections in the United States.</PARA><PARA>Thirdly, and perhaps most critically, this effort requires substantial financial investment. As politicians, we are acutely aware of the numerous important and valuable demands on our budgets. For the past three decades, European nations have enjoyed the luxury of securing their defence at a relatively low cost. Regrettably, that era has come to an end.</PARA><PARA>The stark reality we have faced today is that our safety and the preservation of our democratic values come with a higher price tag. This is not merely about allocating funds for defence. It is about ensuring the robustness of our continent’s economic foundation.</PARA><PARA>Fourthly, Europe needs to be stronger on the world stage. The European Union, our way of thinking and our values are essential in the current geopolitical landscape, as democracy and authoritarians compete over dominance. The EU needs to show its strength globally, especially as China and Russia are bringing forward their own ideas and narratives. We need a stronger European foreign policy and we need to make it more effective, using qualified majority voting in important areas.</PARA><PARA>Dear friends, a strong economy is the bedrock of our security. It enables us to invest in the advanced technologies and capabilities needed to protect our citizens and uphold our way of life. Moreover, a vibrant economy enhances our global influence, allowing us to shape a world order that reflects our values and our interests.</PARA><PARA>Only when our economic base is healthy can we efficiently protect the climate, improve our security and defend ourselves. This is why we need strategic competitiveness. This means building our long-term competitiveness by focusing on our own strengths, deepening the internal market, boosting innovation and focusing on market-based solutions.</PARA><PARA>This is a critical moment. We must be willing to make the hard choices that safeguard our future. Investing in our defence is not just a matter of national security; it is a commitment to the stability and prosperity of our Union. It is about ensuring that Europe remains a beacon of hope and freedom in an increasingly turbulent world.</PARA><PARA>Let us, therefore, approach this challenge not just with the seriousness it demands, but with a sense of shared purpose. Our collective future, the legacy we leave for the next generation, depends on the decisions we make today. Let us invest together in that future, in our security and in the enduring strength of our European Union.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(Applause)</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION><NUMERO ACT="3-094-0000" PRE="3-089-0000" SUIV="3-096-0000" VL="EN" VOD-START="2024-03-13T12:09:10.712" VOD-END="2024-03-13T12:09:25.000"/><INTERVENTION><ORATEUR PP="NULL" LG="EN" MEPID="118859" CODICT="118859" LIB="Roberta | Metsola"><LG>EN</LG><EMPHAS NAME="B">President. – </EMPHAS></ORATEUR><PARA>Thank you very much, Prime Minister Orpo, and thank you to all the colleagues who participated in the debate.</PARA><PARA><EMPHAS NAME="I">(The sitting was briefly suspended)</EMPHAS></PARA></INTERVENTION></CHAPTER>